[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-two]
[第三十二集]
Yannian
延年
Facts are facts.
事实就是事实
Dare to face it?
敢不敢面对
Look at yourself.
看你自己了
enter
进
Yannian
延年
Yes, sir.
先生好
How did you come?
你怎么来了
I heard that you were beaten and hospitalized.
我听说你被打住院了
What, in the way?
怎么样 碍事吗
Thank you, sir. It's out of the way.
谢谢先生店记 不碍事了
I took the risk of visiting to disturb your writing.
我这冒味来访打扰您写字了
You're welcome.
太客气了
The students went on strike.
学生们罢课
I have nothing to do either.
我也没有什么事情做
So I practiced my handwriting.
所以我就练练字
This word of mine
我的这个字
It was influenced by the old gentleman who hated Lai in Nanjing
是受南京仇涞之老先生的影响
With a long-winded sheep's hair
用长锋羊毫
But I still can't mention my wrist.
可我至今不能提腕阿
So your father often criticizes me.
所以你的父亲经常批评我
Words are common to the bone.
字俗入骨
For his words.
为了他这句话
Now I finish writing a knife of shakuhachi paper every day.
我现在每天写完一刀尺八纸
He is a teacher.
他好为人师
Don't argue with him.
您千万别跟他一般见识
Come and sit.
来坐
Help me bring this up.
帮我把这个拿上来
Yannian, you came to me.
延年你来找我
Are you here to plead guilty?
是来问罪的吧
Why do you say that?
您为什么这么说呀
The previous stage
前一阶段
It is widely rumored in the society that your father is immoral.
社会上盛传令尊有失私德
On the basis of dust.
论也是基器尘上
Tang Erhe suggested to Mr. Cai
汤尔和向蔡先生建议
Cancel the senior system in advance
提前取消学长制
Remove Zhongfu from the post of liberal arts senior
免去仲甫文科学长之职
I seconded the motion at that time.
当时我是附议的
I've always regretted this.
为了这件事我一直很后悔
I feel sorry for Zhongfu.
我觉得我对不起仲甫
Yannian, if this is the reason
延年要是因为这件事
Affects the beauty department of your family.
影响了你们家庭的美系
I am willing to make amends to you.
我愿意向你赔罪
sir
先生
Please don't do this. Please sit down.
您您别这样 您请坐
That's it.
是这样
Someone gave me some materials.
有人给我提供了 一些材料
Also said that you and principal Tang are insiders.
还说您跟汤校长是知情人
So I wanted to come.
所以我就想来
Check the situation with you face to face.
当面跟您核实一下这个情况
Someone should have made this up on purpose.
这件事情应该是有人故意编造
untrustworthy
不可信
Zhongfu has really been at the forefront.
仲甫的确一直处在风口浪尖上
This is a fact
这是事实
The title of "New Youth" edited by him is too loud.
他主编的 《新青年》 名头太响
Too much influence
影响太大
Those who oppose it will surely kill them.
反对者必将其置之死地
To achieve this goal.
为达此自的
It's even more extreme.
更是无所不用其极
That principal Tang knows
那汤校长知道
The truth of this matter?
这个事情的真实情况吗
Tang Erhe should also know.
汤尔和也应该知道
This is a deliberate rumor.
这是有人在故意地造谣
Because your father once scolded Tong Er and
因为你的父亲曾经责问过汤尔和
Soup and self-knowledge indefensible dare not answer.
汤尔和自知理亏 不敢回答
Be defeated and flee.
落荒而逃了
Then why did you and Principal Tang propose it?
那您跟汤校长为什么还要提议
Cancel the senior system in advance
提前取消学长制
Yannian, since you asked
延年既然你问了
I'll have a good talk with you about it.
我就和你好好谈一谈这件事
I'm from the same town as Mr Cai.
我和蔡先生是同乡
I'm standing in his shoes.
我是站在他的角度上
Contemplative
考虑问题的
What about your father, honest and frank?
你的父亲呢 性格耿直
Have offended many people.
得罪了很多人
Has become a target of public criticism.
已经成为众矢之的了
To Peking University and to President Cai.
给北大 给蔡校长
Brought a lot of trouble.
带来了很多的麻烦
Since it has been proposed to abolish the senior system.
那既然已经提出要取消学长制
It's better to execute it earlier.
那莫不如早点执行
This will not embarrass Mr. Cai too much.
这样也不会让蔡先生太过难堪
Of course, I am selfish, too.
当然 我也是有私心哪
Zhongfu is irritable and outspoken.
仲甫性格暴躁 口无遮拦
It often makes it difficult for me in public.
经常当众让我难
I don't want him to be my immediate superior.
我不希望他当我的顶头上司
This is my selfishness.
这就是我的私心
Yannian, you're just in time
延年 你来得正好
Let me have a chance to say these words.
让我有机会把这些话说出来
Because these days, because of my selfishness
因为这些天因为我的这点私心
I really can't sleep and regret it.
我真的是寝食难安 后悔莫及
Now I'm even
我现在连
The editorial department of New Youth dare not lose it.
《新青年》 编辑部都不敢丢了
I can only hide here and practice my handwriting.
我只能躲在这儿练练字
Sir, don't blame yourself too much.
先生 您也别太过自责了
Your remarks are of great use to me.
您的这番对我还是用处很大的
Do you think I need to go again?
您觉得我还用不用再去
Ask Principal Tang to check this situation.
找汤校长核实一下这个情况
Principal Tang should think what I think.
汤校长应该和我想的一样
It's all for Mr. Cai's sake.
都是为了蔡先生着想
And he has a grudge against your father.
而他和你的父亲有芥蒂
It's no use looking for him.
你找他也没有什么用
I do remember.
我倒是记得
Shi Zhi specifically investigated this matter.
胡适之专门调查过此事
And refuted Tomer.
并且驳过汤尔和
In that case.
这么看来的话
This fact is not believed.
此事实为不足信
good
好
Thank you, sir. I'll be going now.
谢谢先生 那我就先告辞了
say goodbye to
告辞
Chen Yannian
陈延年
And thoughtful.
又若有所思
Chen Yannian, are you still not well?
陈延年 你是不是还没好啊
Why don't I talk to the nurse
要不我跟护士说说
I'll give you another day, and we'll stay.
再给你开一天 咱接着住
You stuffy gourd!
你这只闷葫芦
The sequelae are so serious.
后遗症这么严重啊
Not a word.
一句话都没有
I'm talking to you, do you hear me?
我跟你说话呢 听见没有
My brain is now.
我现在脑子啊
I'm more awake than ever.
比什么时候都清醒
auntie
姨妈
It's packed.
收拾好了
I called a rickshaw at the door.
我在门口叫了辆黄包车
Let's put the luggage on first.
咱们把行李先放上去吧
Yannian
延年
You sign there. I haven't finished yet.
你在那儿签个字 我还没签完呢
Okay, okay, okay
好行行行
Just leave the hospital.
刚出院你就别管了
I'll do it. I'll do it
我来我来
I'll do it. I can do it.
我来 我可以的
Mrs Chen
陈夫人
Please sign your name.
麻烦您签个字
If a gentleman named Zhang comes to me
如果有一位姓张的先生来找我
Please forward this letter to him.
请把这封信转交给他
come on
走吧
What about luggage?
行李呢
Liu Mei took it all out.
柳眉都拿出去了
Ah, brother
老弟啊
Why did you make an appointment with such a place?
你怎么约了这么个地方
Yamanaka
这山路崎
It's all this way.
又这么大老远的
It made me nervous for a while.
弄得我紧张了好一阵子
How's your head? Are you feeling better?
怎么样 头好点了吗
All healed.
都痊愈了
that's good
那就好
How about that? Have you verified it?
怎么样那个事你核实了没有
Am I lying?
我没说谎吧
I looked for both of them.
他们两个人我都找了
Just like you said.
跟你说的一样
Honestly, when I first found out about this,
说实话手 我刚知道这个事的时候
I was so angry that I almost fainted
气得都快晕过去了
What are you going to do, brother?
老弟那你准备怎么办
What can I do?
我能怎么办
Take my brother to the French press.
带着我弟弟赶紧去法压
Leave this place.
离开这个是之地
You have to escape.
你要逃避啊
This is not your quality, Chen Yannian.
这可不是你陈延年的品质啊
What do you suggest I do?
那你说我该怎么办
I think
我觉得
You should at least come forward.
你至少应该站出来
Persuade your father to admit his mistake
规劝你的父亲承认错误
give up evil and return to virtue—turn over a new leaf
改邪归正
Don't influence and corrupt again.
不要再影响和败坏
The reputation of the student movement.
学生运动的声誉了
Chen Duxiu, if he can listen to my advice
他陈独秀要是能听我劝
He's not Chen Duxiu.
他就不是陈独秀了
He's been like this all his life, and he can't change it.
这辈子他就这样了 改不了
Then we should all the more.
那我们就更应该
Tell the truth to the people.
把这个真相告诉民众啊
What you said earlier
你之前说的
If everyone knows about this,
这个事要是让大家都知道了
It is a devastating blow to the student movement.
对学生运动是毁灭性的打击
right
对
And now you're saying
现在你又说
To make this public.
要把这个事公布出去
You are inconsistent.
你这是前后矛盾啊
No, no, it's not contradictory at all.
不不不 一点也不矛盾
Bro, don't break or stand.
老弟 不破不立呀
Instead of letting students exercise
与其让学生运动
Destroyed by Chen Duxiu's hand
毁在陈独秀的手上
Why don't we overthrow him first and set up another leader?
倒不如我们先推翻他 另立领袖
Set up another leader
另立领袖
Who is it?
立谁啊
Peking University Academic Union
北大 学联
So many respected professors.
那么多德高望重的教授
Any one can do it.
随便拎一个都能胜任啊
Okay, what you said is also reasonable.
行你说的也有道理
Then let me get this straight.
那我就直说了
What's in it for me?
这么做我有什么好处
any
什么
I can't believe you want benefits.
你 你竟然会要好处
I have recognized it now.
我现在已经认清了
He really looks like Chen Duxiu.
他陈独秀的真面冒
What patriotic student movement?
什么爱国 学生运动
It's a joke.
简直就是个笑话
Now that I have decided to go to France.
既然我已经决定好了要去法国
Then I must plan for myself in the future.
那我肯定得为自己以后打算打算
I said, bro.
我说老弟
You have changed too much.
你这变化也太大了
I'm a little uncomfortable.
我有点不适应啊
What do you mean?
你什么意思呀
Not you
不是你
Do you like to adapt?
你爱适应不适应
I didn't say it wouldn't benefit you.
我也没说不给你好处啊
such
这样
As long as you and Chen Qiaonian
只要你和陈乔年
Sign this statement.
在这个声明上签个字
See the newspaper tomorrow.
明天一见报纸
I'll help you two right away.
我立即帮你们哥俩办好
Procedures for studying in France
去法国留学的手续
What do you think?
你看如何
What signature is so valuable?
什么签名 这么值钱
This is one.
这是一张
Expose Chen Duxiu's moral corruption
揭露陈独秀道德败坏
And a statement declaring his separation from father and son.
和宣布与他脱离父子关系的声明
Don't worry
你放心
This is the right thing to do.
这是正义之举
It will never affect the image of your two brothers.
绝对不会影响你们哥俩的形象
Are you serious about this?
你这话当真吗
take seriously
当真
OK, I can sign this word
行这个字我可以签
But you have to promise me two conditions.
但是你得答应我两个条件
You said
你说
First, studying abroad is done at public expense.
第一 留学办成公费的
This is no problem.
这个没问题
Second, give me 500 dollars.
第二 再给我五百大洋
Dude, this is a lion's big mouth
老弟 你这可是狮子大开口啊
If you can promise
你要是能答应
I can sign this word now.
这个字我现在就可以签
Don't hesitate either.
你也别犹豫了
Okay, I promise.
行我答应
Say it empty.
空说啊
Make a written statement without any evidence.
空口无凭 立个字据
Liu Mei just set me up a few days ago.
前几天柳眉刚套过我的话
You want to set me up again?
你还想再算计我
You really treat me like a fool.
你们真把我当大傻子了
Let me tell you something, Chen Yannian
我告诉你陈延年
I will never set up this written document.
这个字据我绝对不会立
If you want to do this
要想办成这个事
This time tomorrow or
明天还是这个时间
Or this place?
还是这个地方
I promise you five hundred dollars.
我保证给你五百大洋
As for studying in France.
至于去法国留学的事
This is too big. Please allow me two days.
这个事太大了 你容我两天时间
But I promise.
不过我保证
I Zhang Fengzai keep my word.
我张丰载说话算话
stay away
躲开
Guo's bones are not cold.
老郭户骨未寒
I have to kill him today. I
我今天非得弄死他我
calm
冷静
What are you doing?
干什么呀
It's all classmates. Don't get killed
都是同学 别出人命了
What kind of life is it?
出什么人命啊
I told you so.
早就跟你说了
The weak can't be tough.
弱的不行来硬的
Chen Yannian, is it interesting for you to do this?
陈延年 你这么做有意思吗
You two brothers are in front of us today
你们兄弟俩今天当着我们的面
Make a deal with her, right?
跟他做交易是不是
What kind of deal do I make?
我做什么交易啊
CSI: What do you need to say?
老何你费什么话
Do it
干吧
Wait!
等等等
Come here!
你给我过来
What's the situation?
什么情况啊
Which show are you playing?
你们这是演的哪一出啊
Singing red and white faces with me here
跟我这儿唱红白脸呢
Red and white face
红白脸
Today, I will give you a bad face.
老子今天给你唱黑脸
Kill you and chop you up.
要了你的命 劈了你
Dare you
你敢
Do you know who I am?
知道我什么身份吗
I don't care what your status is.
我管你什么身份
Tell you.
告诉你们
I'm the metropolitan police department.
我可是京师警察厅
Deputy head of the intelligence unit
情报组的副组长
You touched me and tried to cut me.
你们动我一下试试 还砍我
Come and chop here.
来 往这儿砍
If I look at my eyes
我要是一下眼睛
I am your grandson
我是你孙子
grandchild
孙子
Grandpa, I'll cut you down today.
爷爷我今儿就砍了你
Letter from my hometown.
老家来信儿了
Tomorrow I will go back to Shandong to marry my daughter-in-law.
明儿我就回山东娶媳妇去
I did a big job before I left today.
今天我临走之前干一票大的
It kills you.
要了你的命
Give Guo a ride on the road.
给老郭路上搭个伴儿
step aside
起开
Give Guo a companion. You're looking for Bai Lan.
给老郭搭伴你找白兰呀
What do you want with me?
你找我干吗
Chop your grandson.
劈了你 这孙子
kneel
跪下
Aauto Quicker, put it down.
快快快手放下
Come down and kneel down.
你下来跪下
Yannian, say something, Yannian
延年 你说句话 延年
He has promised to write it.
他已经答应写了
Is it Zhang Fengzai?
是不是 张丰载
Yes, yes, yes
对对对
I'll write it now. I'll write it right away
我现在就写 我马上就写
You two dig a hole. Go
你俩挖坑去 快去啊
Go and take it.
去呀 拿着
Don't hurt anyone.
千万别伤人啊
Don't get killed
别出人命啊
Come on, guys.
不至于吧 哥几个
Don't hurt anyone, don't kill anyone.
别伤人 千万别出人命
Yannian
延年
Yannian, say something, Yannian
延年 你说句话 延年
You two stay away.
你俩离远点
Don't spill all your blood.
别溅你们一身血
Don't kill yourself to tell you.
千万别出人命 告诉你
Give me an account of this today.
今天把这个事给我一五一十
Write it all down clearly for me.
全部给我写清楚
Okay, I'll write. I'll write
好 好 我写我写
If you dare to leave a word behind
你要是敢落下一个字
I'll take it off for you.
我腿给你卸了它
I write, I write.
我写 我写
come on
快点
Write, I write, I write, I write right away.
写写 我写我写 马上就写
I'm writing it, Yannian
我写着呢 延年
Stop digging, Yannian. I'm writing it.
别挖了 延年我写着呢
Take a break, Yannian
你歇歇手 延年
You can write it.
你写呀倒是
Fine. Then what
行行 那什么
Don't get killed
别出人命啊
What? I remember
那什么 我记得
When that night
当 当那天晚上
Is it eleven o'clock or twelve o'clock
约摸着是十一点还是十二点
Exactly what time?
到底几点
half past eight
八点半
Yeah, yeah, 8: 30.
对 对对 八点半
At 8: 30, we and Yannian
八点半手 我们和延年
half past eight
八点半
Don't laugh and dig.
别笑 好好挖
Do a full set of plays
做戏做全套
Such an important thing
这么重要的事
Why don't you discuss it?
你们怎么也不商量一下
Act without authorization.
就擅自行动
How dangerous it is in case something happens!
万一出了事多危险啊
We consider this matter.
我们考虑到这件事情
Mr. Zhongfu can't know
不能让仲甫先生知道
I'm afraid something big will happen with his temper.
以他的脾气恐怕会出大事
Now the struggle has entered
现在斗争已经进入到了
White-hot stage
白热化阶段
In order to deal with the general strike of the reactionary government
反动政府为了对付总罢课
Various differentiation methods have been adopted.
采取了多种分化手段
Win over many teachers and students.
拉拢了不少师生
You should report this situation to the Federation of Students at once.
你们要把这个情况马上报告学联
Let them think about countermeasures.
让他们思考对策
At the same time.
同时做好
Mental preparation for large-scale repression
应对大规模镇压的思想准备
Ok, Zhong Jie and I will go to the meeting of the Federation of Students later.
好 我和仲解一会儿去学联开会
We want to give Zhang Fengzai's statement.
我们想把张丰载的口供
Give it to the newspaper for publication.
交给报社刊登出来
Do you think it's feasible?
您觉得可行吗
agree
同意
At this time, we have to be tit for tat.
这个时候就得针锋相对
According to Zhang Fengzai
据张丰载交代
The police department has sent you and Mr. Zhongfu
警察厅已经将您和仲甫先生
Be included in the investigation list
列入调查名单
And submitted it to the presidential palace.
并且向总统府提交了
Banning the National and Weekly Review
取缔《国民》 《每周评论》
Wait for an application from a magazine.
等杂志的申请
You must pay attention to safety.
您一定要注意安全
Go ahead and get busy.
你去忙吧
Go to your father.
找一趟你爸爸
Grinding scissors
磨剪子
kitchen knife
菜刀
Kitchen knife
饯菜刀
Grinding scissors
磨剪子
You're going to put
一会儿你要把
寿昌来了
守常来了
What's up?
什么事
Is brother Zhongfu here?
仲甫兄在吗
It's in the study. I've been writing all day
在书房呢 都写了一天了
What's the matter
出什么事了
中富兄
仲甫兄
How did you come?
你怎么来了
Let me discuss something with you.
我跟你商量点事
What's up?
什么事
Fire that Zhang Fengzai from Peking University.
北大开除那个张丰载
You remember, right?
你还记得吧
I remember. Why?
我记得 怎么了
Now I've changed.
人家现在摇身一变
He became a spy of the Metropolitan Police Department.
成了京师警察厅的密探了
Trying to woo Yannian against you
想拉拢延年来反对你
And the result?
结果呢
Let Yannian ask you a lot about the gums.
让延年反问出来很多龈的内情
Charcoal, they have an idea
世炭他们有个想法
Want to make these things public
想把这些东西公布于众
What do you think?
你觉得呢
A matter of great satisfaction.
大快人心的事
But as a result.
但是这么一来
It can be easily caused.
可很容易引起
A strong reaction from the reactionary government.
反动政府的强烈反弹
I met a dog in front of your house just now.
刚才我在你家门口可遇见狗了
I see
我知道
They just sent a few cats with full feet.
他们就派那么几个整脚猫过来
You really don't look down on me, Chen Duxiu
真是不把我陈独秀放在眼里了
Not brother Zhongfu
不是 仲甫兄
I know you're not afraid.
我呢 知道你不怕
I'm not afraid either.
我也不怕
We are both blacklisted people.
咱俩都是上了黑名单的人
If you have me here, you can't live without me there.
你这儿有了 我那儿也少不了
But have you thought about one thing?
但是有一件事你想过没有
Say if something happens to us
假如说咱俩要是出了事
I'm sorry for your life.
你我之性命倒是不足为惜
Bear the brunt
首当其冲的
But "New Youth"
可就是 《新青年》
And the Weekly Review.
还有《每周评论》
And the student movement, which is now gaining momentum.
和眼下势头正猛的学生运动啊
I see
我知道
Are you trying to tell me
你是想告诉我
It's best to retreat now.
眼下最好以退为进
Don't show your face yet, right?
暂时不要出头露面 对吗
Makes sense. I agree.
有道理 我同意
But I can't stay at home and have long hair.
可是我总不能憋在家里长毛吧
I have to order something.
我总得千点什么吧
I have arranged it for you.
我者替你安排好了
What about next week
下周呢
I'm the rotation editor of New Youth.
我是 《新青年》 的轮流值编
But I have too many things to do.
但是我手里的事太多 忙不过来
Let's take turns.
咱俩人轮换一下
line
行
Eagle Zhang Fengzai confessed himself.
鹰犬张丰载自供状
Now the reporter put the gate of the Metropolitan Police Department
现在记者把京师警察厅的大门
It's all blocked.
都堵上了
How do you want me to explain it to people?
你让我怎么跟人解释
inspector general
总监
You have to make decisions for me this time.
这回您可得给我做主啊
You don't know Chen Yannian's gang.
您是不知道 陈延年那帮人
That's a gang member!
那简直就是帮会分子啊
I was beaten.
人被打了
I lost my face and wrote a confession.
脸丢尽了 写了自供状
In the newspaper
上了报
You sold the whole police department.
整个警察厅全让你给出卖了
What kind of gang members are you making up now?
现在还编什么帮会分子了
You're so talented.
你太有才了
You don't know how hard they are.
您是不知道他们下手有多狠
I almost dug a hole and buried it.
差点给我刨坑埋了
You are a softie.
你就是个软蛋
Let people frighten hiss twice.
让人家吓嘘了两下
Just like this.
就变成这个样子
The reporter will be back at the gate now.
现在记者就在大门回
You explain it, you explain it to me.
你去解释 你去给我解释去
My subordinates met gang members.
属下遇到了帮会分子
You can't come back if you don't say it.
不说可就回不来了
Beat it into confession.
屈打成招啊
What do you mean?
你什么意思
Why don't you know yourself?
您怎么就不明自呢
Gang members control the student movement.
帮会分子控制了学生运动
Caught a newspaper reporter.
抓了报社记者
For the journalist's life.
记者为了活命
Have to follow their request.
不得不按他们的要求
Confess to being a member of the National Police Department.
供认自己是警察厅的人
This is the truth.
这就是真相啊
confess to false charges under torture
屈打成招
It seems that this can only be the case now.
现在看来只能是这样了
Come on, you made all this up
行了 你把你编的这一切
Write materials for me.
都给我写成材料
I gave it to Qian Nengxun as evidence.
我交给钱能训作为证据
Gang members colluded with the student movement.
帮会分子勾结学生运动
This name is good enough for them to drink a pot.
这个名目好 够他们喝一壶的
inspector general
总监
What are you?
你这是什么
The materials have already been prepared.
材料早就准备好了
You are really a good material.
你真是块好材料啊
Director Wu Director Wu
吴总监 吴总监
Come on, the reporters can't stop it.
快点 记者们都拦不住了
Let them wait.
让他们等着
Did you see that?
你瞧见了没有
I have to wipe your ass at this time.
这个时候我还得替你擦屁股
Stay away from the press.
一边待着去 别让记者看见
Shouchang Yannian told me everything.
守常 延年都跟我说了
You should be careful yourself these days.
这几天你自己也要当心一点
Don't worry on my side, sister-in-law.
我这边您放心吧嫂子
Now the key is brother Zhongfu's side.
现在 关键是仲甫兄这边
You have to watch him.
您可得看好他
I see
我知道
Yannian
延年
I also give you a task.
我也交给你一个任务
Your father is now in the government.
你父亲现在是政府的
A thorn in one's side
眼中钉 肉中刺
You know his temperament.
他的脾气秉性你知道
Be sure to watch him.
一定看好他
good
好
Then I'll go back
那我回了
good-bye
慢走
Since our family has been targeted.
既然咱们家被町上了
Just don't go out.
你们就都别出去了
That won't do.
那可不行
We have to call on the people to boycott Japanese goods.
我们还得号召民众抵制日货呢
What if you have something to do when you are so young?
你那么小 出去有个事怎么办
The benefits of small games
小有小的好处
The police won't go after children.
警察不会町上小孩的
No, stay at home.
不行 都在家待着
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报 卖报 卖报
看陈独秀李大钊发文
看陈独秀 李大钊发文
Angry and arrogant
怒斥小蛮横
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报 卖报 卖报
陈独秀李大钊发文
陈独秀 李大钊发文
Be angry and rude
怒斥小幡蛮横
看陈独秀李大钊发文
看陈独秀 李大钊发文
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报 卖报
ladies and gentlemen
诸位
Yesterday, America, Britain, France and Italy Day
昨天美英法意日
Ministers of several countries in China
几国驻华公使
A protest note was sent to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China.
联合向我外交部提出了抗议照会
And asked us to understand what happened recently.
并要求我们对近日所发生的
Personal attacks on expatriates from various countries
对诸国侨民遭受人身攻击事件
Explain and make peace.
进行解释和道
I'm talking about these events.
我说诸位 这些事件
Today, we have to develop one.
我们今天必须研究出一个
operable
切实可行的
The operational scheme comes out.
可以操作的方案出来
Let's invite Premier Qian.
下面 就请钱总理
Tell everyone about the general situation.
把总的形势给大家说一说
As far as the situation in Beijing is concerned
就北京的形势而言
Since the last drastic measures were taken
自上次采取严厉措施以后
The situation has improved.
情况有所好转
Many graduating classes in Beijing.
北京不少学校毕业班
Have resumed classes to prepare for the exam.
已经复课准备考试
There are many students.
还有不少学生
Start preparing for the civil service advanced examination.
开始准备文官高等考试
After the schools have an early holiday
各学校提前放假之后
Many students have also left Beijing.
也有不少学生离开了北京
but
但是
The general strike in 33 schools is still going on.
三十三个学校的总罢课仍在进行
Although students didn't take to the streets recently
学生近日虽然没有上街游行
Demonstrations and speeches
示威和演讲
They changed their ways.
他们变换了方式
Boycott Japanese goods in the name of selling domestic goods
以卖国货为名进行抵制日货
And encourage publicity activities.
和鼓动宣传活动
There are signs that
有迹象表明
Students are engaged in a tug of war with the government.
学生在和政府进行拉锯战
Trying to drag the student movement into the normal state.
试图把学生运动拖入常态
Hope to get the southern government
希望得到南方政府
And other cities across the country.
和全国其他城市的支持
To form a prairie fire.
以形成燎原之势
If no decisive action is taken
如不采取断然行动
It's bound to end.
势必不可收场
As far as the whole country is concerned
就全国而言
Now Shanghai has implemented a general strike.
现在上海已经实行了总罢课
Nanjing, Wuhan, Changsha and other places
天津 南京 武汉 长沙等地
There have also been strikes.
也都出现了罢课
Shanghai Chamber of Commerce Students Federation, etc.
上海商会 学生联合会等
Full mobilization is under way.
正在进行全面动员
Let it go.
如任其发展下去
Shanghai is probably the same as Beijing.
上海很有可能和北京一样
Become the second center of the student movement
成为学生运动的第二个中心
Students from both sides of Japan and South China meet.
日南北两边学生合流
Students from both sides of Dan River meet.
旦南北两边学生合流
That would be a terrible thing.
那将是十分可怕的事情
Japanese ministers protested in succession.
日本公使接连抗议
The Japanese army is eager to move.
日本军队鑫鑫欲动
Britain and America were originally neutral.
英美法三国本来处于中立
But recently, it has joined forces with Japan to oppress.
但近日 已有和日本联手压迫
Signs of the Chinese government
中国政府的迹象
This shows the order of all countries towards Beijing.
这说明各国对北京的秩序
Serious dissatisfaction has lost patience.
严重不满 已经失去了耐心
You two have analyzed the situation thoroughly.
两位对形势分析得很透彻了
Let me summarize.
我总结一下啊
first
第一
The drastic measures we have taken have paid off.
我们采取的严厉措施收到成效了
Compared with the situation before and in the middle of the month.
自前的情况和月中比
Much more relaxed.
缓和得多了
What does it mean?
说明了什么呢
It shows that students are also bullying.
说明学生也是欺软怕硬的
second
第二
This student movement has dragged on for so long.
这个学生运动拖了这么久了
Endurance in all aspects has reached its limit.
各方面的忍耐力已经到了极限了
It's time to end it.
已经到了该了断的时候了
When you don't stop, you will suffer from chaos.
当断不断 反受其乱
So tomorrow I will issue a presidential decree.
所以 明天我要发布大总统令
Take tough measures to force schools to resume classes.
采取强硬措施 强令学校复课
Students are not allowed to use any name or excuse.
不许学生以任何名自和借口
Shangjie activity
上街活动
Violator hell to pay
违令者 严惩不贷
The specific situation is coordinated by Premier Qian.
具体情况由钱总理统一协调
Garrison headquarters, the metropolitan police department.
强令京师警察厅 警备司令部
There is also a coordinated execution of the step army at the head of the door.
还有步军统领门协同执行
If you have no objection.
如果各位没什么异议
We can finish the meeting.
我们就可以散会了
President, I want to talk to you alone.
大总统 我想单独和您聊聊
president
大总统
The new step army leads Wang Huaiqing.
新任步军统领王怀庆
And the garrison commander Duan Zhigui.
以及警备司令段芝贵
I've been waiting for you for half a day.
等您半天了
Let them wait.
让他们再等等吧
be
是
president
大总统
Take such drastic measures now.
现在采取这样的严厉措施
Give Wang Huaiqing back.
还让王怀庆
Replace Li Changtai as the leader of the infantry.
取代李长泰做步军统领
I wonder if the president has considered the consequences?
不知大总统考虑过后果没有
At this meeting just now
这刚才会上
Don't you advocate being tough?
你不是主张强硬的吗
How did it change at a glance?
怎么一眼就变了
Do you need to be tough enough?
可是否需要强硬到
Police, gendarmes, troops together.
警察 宪兵 军队一起出动
Brother Ju Ren
菊人兄
Wang Huaiqing is known as the butcher.
这王怀庆可是号称屠夫啊
Duan Zhigui barks every day.
段芝贵更是天天叫
Ten years rather than school.
宁可十年不要学校
This style of study can't be tolerated for a day.
不可一日容此学风
At this time, you let them join hands to direct the suppression.
这个时候你让他们联手指挥镇压
It won't end well in the future
将来不好收场啊
Duan Qirui insisted that
是段祺瑞坚持让
Wang Huaiqing and Duan Zhigui did it.
王怀庆和段芝贵出马的
I can't help it
我也没办法
And what about Paris?
还有巴黎那边怎么办
It will be published tomorrow.
明天就要发表
Reject Cao Rulin Zhang Zongxiang Lu Zong
拒绝曹汝霖 章宗祥 陆宗
Presidential decree of resignation
辞职的大总统令
It's not easy to explain.
论可不好交代呀
What's the use of telling me this now?
你现在跟我说这些有什么用啊
Why didn't you say so at the meeting?
那会上你怎么不说呀
I only grumbled a few words in front of Brother Ju.
我除了在菊人兄面前发几句牢骚
What else can you do?
还能有什么作为啊
You complain to me.
你跟我发牢骚
I don't even know where to cry.
我还都不知道找什么地方哭呢
The country has reached this point.
国家都到这个地步了
What can we do?
我们能有什么作为
Take it one step at a time.
走一步看一步吧
I can't. Let's go together.
实在不行 咱俩一块滚蛋
Why is this army here?
这军队怎么在这儿
Ah, what's going on
是啊怎么回事
So many troops are here.
这么多军队在这儿呢
Get out of the way
让开 让开
No, they're going to do it.
不好 他们要下黑手了
We have to hurry back to the red chamber.
我们得赶紧回红楼
Listen to me.
听我说
I'll find Mr. Shouchang.
我去找守常先生
You guys get together in the library.
你们几个赶紧去图书馆集合
Inform each class
通报各班
Go, go!
快去走
Haiwei
海威
Go to the front door and find Zilan.
你去前门找自兰
They sell domestic products there.
他们在那儿卖国货
Go quickly. Something will happen to them.
你赶紧去 他们要出事
OK, don't worry.
行放心吧
hurry up
行方 放心吧
Here you are.
来给您
Thank you for supporting domestic products.
谢谢您支持国货
There are toothbrushes and tooth powder.
有牙刷牙粉
This is canned food from Guanshengyuan.
这是冠生园的罐头
Give me a support.
支持一下
Support domestic products
支持国货
Please buy a toothpaste.
您买个牙膏吧
Give it a support.
支持一下吧
Hello, have some domestic products.
您好 来点国货吧
Thank you
谢谢  谢谢
Safeguard sovereignty and support domestic products
维护主权 支持国货
Support domestic products, please.
支持国货 支持一下吧
Bai LanBai Lan
白兰白兰
自兰白兰
自兰 白兰
Run!
快跑快跑
run for it
快跑
cut it
快走
give me myself
放开我
He Mengxiong
何孟雄
Qunxian
群先
Group, leave me alone. Let's go
群先你别管我 快走
Be honest.
老实点
give me myself
放开我
Why arrest me?
凭什么抓我
Qunxian
群先
give me myself
放开我
Let her go!
放开她
Qunxian
群先
Tell me about the students.
说说学生的情况吧
Beijing xuelian
北京学联
I just had a meeting in the auditorium of a normal university.
刚在高等师范学校的礼堂开了会
decide unanimously
一致决定
Resume the large-scale speech activity tomorrow.
明天恢复大规模的演讲活动
It is estimated that thousands of people will take to the streets.
估计会有几千人上街
Now all schools are preparing overnight.
现在各个学校都在连夜准备
the highest official rank in imperial China
一品
Report the situation of Peking University to the director.
你给总监汇报一下北大的情况
good
好
Students of Peking University are now making
北大的学生现在正在制作
Small white flag and slogan
小白旗和标语口号
Prepare for tomorrow's speech
准备明天的演讲
According to this situation.
照这个阵势来看
Fake and Ma Temple in the Red Mansion of Peking University
北大红楼 法科和马神庙
These three places
这三个地方
It is estimated that there will be about 500 people tomorrow.
明天估计会有五百人左右
These students are really not afraid of death.
这些学生还真有不怕死的
We arrested seventy people today.
今天我们抓了七十个人
The detention center is full.
看守所已经关满了
What should I do tomorrow?
明天该怎么办啊
Then don't catch it.
那不抓了
Of course, I will.
当然要抓了
I think the red building of Peking University is fine.
我看北大红楼可以
It can hold a thousand people.
能装一千个人呢
Of course, the red chamber can't be too conspicuous.
红楼当然不可以 太扎眼了
And those people are professors.
而且那些人都是些教授
We won't be able to mess with them for a while.
咱们一时半会儿还惹不起他们
I think it's ok for Peking University Law Department along the North River.
北河沿的北大法科 我看行吧
It's also close there.
那儿距离也近
Are the troops stationed in the old section of the North Riverside?
北河沿是不是驻着老段的部队啊
There are ten tents on each side of the school gate.
是校门两边各十个帐篷
Okay, North Riverside, then.
好那就北河沿吧
Notify Duan Zhigui and Wang Huaiqing
通知段芝贵和王怀庆
Get them ready.
让他们做好准备
Let's give 70% of the police force tomorrow.
明天咱们出七成的警力
Post-genius is the key.
后天才是重点
I'm afraid we'll have to go out.
恐怕得全员出动
leave it at that
就这样吧
be
是
Wait, wait, wait
等等 等等 等等
Come back!
回来回来
keep in mind
记住了
Let's get these students
咱们是让这些学生
Go back where you came from.
从哪儿出来的再回到哪儿去
Understand?
明白吧
It's called control, not arrest
这叫管制 不叫逮捕
clear
明白
Go
去吧
We reclaim Qingdao's diplomacy.
我们索回青岛的外交
Not because of the defeat.
既不是因为打了败仗
It's not like encroaching on someone else's taxi land.
又不是去侵占别人的士地
Why does the government ban it?
政府为什么要禁止
What about the national patriotic movement?
国民卫国的运动呢
Now we can't help but send out
我们现在忍不住要发出
A pitiful voice.
极悲惨可怜的声音
Advise the military and police compatriots
奉劝军警诸同胞
It's the same root. Why rush it?
本是同根生 相煎何太急
Keep your voice down
小声点
Your dad just fell asleep after writing all night last night.
你爸昨晚上写了一宿刚睡着
Chen Boqiao writes really well.
陈伯俏写得可真好
Chen Bai writes really well.
陈佰佰写得可真好
Chen writes really well.
陈俏俏写得可真好
伯母我来
姨妈 我来
So many!
姨妈 马我来
Qiaonian
乔年
We went to the street today.
今天咱俩上大街上
How about reading this passage to the police?
把这段朗诵给警察听 怎么样
Well, maybe the police will be moved to tears.
好啊说不定警察就要感动哭了
impossible
不行
The police go to the streets to arrest and beat people.
警察上街要抓人打人的
You two girls must not go to the streets.
你们俩女孩千万不能上街啊
That won't do.
那可不行
I haven't seen any big waves before.
什么大风大浪没见过呀
This little storm can't beat me.
这点小风浪 难不倒我
Don't beat you.
难不倒你
I told you not to go out.
我跟你说 不许出去
Nobody goes out today.
今天谁也不许出去
I didn't sleep well all night.
晚上我一晚上都没睡好
Lao Meng Meng qun xian
老梦见群先
I don't know where she's locked up.
也不知道她关到哪儿去了
No news at all.
一点消息都没有
I'm so anxious.
急死人了
Yannian
延年
Keep your voice down
小声点
Your husband is sleeping.
你先生在睡觉呢
Have you got the news of Qunxian?
你有群先的消息了没有
I haven't heard of it yet.
暂时没听说
But I heard that
不过我听说
They seem to be locked in the metropolitan police department.
他们好像关在京师警察厅
I've been to that place, and I have books to read.
那地方我去过 还有书看呢
I think Qunxian should be fine.
我觉得群先应该没事
This silly child
这个傻孩子
This time the situation is different from last time.
这次情况和上次不一样啊
Yannian
延年
李大钊先生和邓中夏
李大钊先生和邓中夏
Let me tell you specially.
让我特意告诉你
Never go out today.
今天千万不要出门
Be sure to stay at home with Mr. Zhongfu.
一定要在家里陪着仲甫先生
Okay, okay, okay. Got it
行行行 知道了
Bai Lan
白兰
Shanghai and Guangzhou will hold a memorial service for Xingang.
上海和广州要为心刚开追悼会
You also prepare.
你也准备一下
Okay, I got it
好我知道了
Come to Hewei and get two eggs.
来海威拿两个鸡蛋
I'll bring you some steamed stuffed buns.
我再给你带点包子
Bring it to the students to eat. Do you hear me?
给同学们拿过去吃 听到没
good
好
Please don't
千万别能
Run to Dashilan for business when you are in danger.
千方别ä能
There are too many shops to get in.
那儿商铺多 马队进不去
Okay, okay, know
行行行 知道
I've sorted everything out.
我都整理好了
Okay, okay, let's go then
好的好的 那我们走了
Ah, be careful!
小心啊
good
好
I'm leaving too.
我也走了
I'll go too. I'll go too.
我也去 我也去
Qiaonian
乔年
You two are not allowed to go.
你俩不许去
Haiwei
海威
What's going on? You guys
怎么回事你们
I thought I told you not to go out.
不是让你们不出去吗
Why aren't you obedient?
怎么都不听话呢
Everybody go back!
都给我回去
go
走
Why don't I deliver steamed stuffed bun?
要不我去给送包子吧
I'm still out. Stay
还出去呢 待着去
Hurry up, hurry up!
快点 快点 快点
Why arrest us?
凭什么抓我们
come on
快点
Why push me?
凭什么推我
Our actions are all patriotic.
我们的行为全都是爱国的行为
What makes you push me?
你凭什么推我
quisling
卖国贼
Are you Chinese?
你们是不是中国人
Are you still not Chinese?
你还是不是中国人你
cut it
快走
What crime have we committed? Tell me.
我们犯什么罪了 你告诉我
What crime have we committed?
我们犯什么罪了
quisling
卖国贼
get in
进去
Don't push me.
别推我
Do you still have a conscience?
你还有没有良心啊
Don't do it.
别动手
Give me my freedom, give me my freedom
还我自由 还我自由
Student prison. Student prison
学生监狱 学生监狱
All of you stay here.
都给我老实待着
Write another one.
再写一个
Write again and write again
再写 再写
Student prison. Student prison
学生监狱 学生监狱
You belong to the dog, right?
你属狗的吧你
You are the dog.
你才是狗
Love China and defend China
爱我中华保卫中国
What's the matter?
怎么来了
Auntie, give you a brain tonic.
姨妈给您补补脑
good
好
sit down
坐下
Just this day, no one spoke to me.
正好这一天也没人搭理我了
Sit down and I'll talk to you.
你坐下我跟你聊聊
I'll call auntie for you.
我给您叫姨妈去
Just you.
坐下就你
Sit down, Jing. Just you.
坐下京 就你
I'm editing the next issue of New Youth.
我在编辑下一期的 《新青年》
What do you always feel short of?
总觉得缺点什么
I want to write a letter.
我想写封信
Mainly to clarify.
主要是想澄清
Two issues that everyone is concerned about.
两个大家都比较关心的问题
What problem?
什么问题
In the new culture movement.
是在新文化运动中
Debate between reformers and conservatives
革新派和保守派的争论
What kind of question is it?
是个什么性质的问题
Second, we reformed the old Chinese learning.
第二 是我们革新派对中国旧学
What is the attitude?
究竟是什么态度
I'm also interested in these two questions.
这两个问题我也感兴趣
Tell me about it.
您跟我说说
be interested in
感兴趣
Well, listen to me and tell you something.
那好 你听我好好跟你说说
First, I propose
第一 我提出
Debate between reformers and conservatives
革新派和保守派的争论
Is a phenomenon of academic progress.
是一种学术的进步现象
It's an academic dispute, not between us.
是学术之争 不是敌我之分
For example, Chen DuxiuLi Dazhao of Peking University
比如北大陈独秀李大钊
Shiluxun Qian Xuantong
胡适 鲁迅 钱玄同
With Gu Hongming Liu Shipei
跟辜鸿铭 刘师培
The dispute between Huang and Ni
黄倪之间的争论
It is of this nature.
它就是这种性质
That's not what Huang Kan thinks.
那黄侃可不是这么想的
His language is too vicious.
他那语言太恶毒了
There are different arguments.
争论问题 各已见
Different opinions are expressed in the debate.
争论问题 各抒己见
Even the two sides will scold a few words.
甚至双方会骂几句
This is normal.
这属于正常的
Throughout the history of countries around the world
纵观世界各国的历史
The development of new culture
新文化的发展
Have this process.
都有这个过程
Reformists and conservatives are relative.
革新派和保守派是相对的
Today's conservatives
今日的保守派
Maybe he used to be an innovator.
从前可能也是革新派
Today's innovators
今日的革新派
Maybe become a conservative in the future.
将来也许会变成保守派
There is no end to the evolution of the world.
世界进化的大流尚没有止境
So the struggle between the reformers and the conservatives
那么革新派和保守派的抗争
There is no end to it.
也便没有止期
Even in another million years.
即使再过一百万年
A foot above the road is a foot above the devil.
道高一尺 魔高一丈
The world is innovative and conservative after all.
世界终究是革新和保守的
The world of struggle
抗争之世界
Look, today, we are reformers.
你今天看 我们是革新派
Gu Ming, they are conservative
辜鸿铭他们是保守的
The environment will change tomorrow.
明天环境变了
Maybe it will be reversed.
也许就会颠倒到过来
This is the historical view of evidence.
这是证的历史观
What do you mean?
那您的意思是
Maybe one day Gu Hongming's point of view
也许有一天辜鸿铭的观点
May also be correct.
也可能是正确的
First you have to admit
首先你要承认
Hongming Liu Shipei Huang Kan
辜鸿铭 刘师培 黄侃
They are all people with specialized knowledge.
他们都是有专门学问的人
Secondly, even today.
其次 即便是今天
Some of their views are also reasonable.
他们说的一些观点也有一定的合理性
Our fight with them again
再次 我们和他们的争斗
In the final analysis, it is the need of social change.
说到底是社会变革的需要
At a certain time
到了一定时候
Living conditions have changed.
生活条件变了
People's understanding of the dispute between the old and the new
人们对新旧之争的认识
Will also change.
也会发生变化
It will even reverse.
甚至会逆转
Do you understand
你听明白了吗
Then I understand what you said.
那您这么说我听明白了
What's your second question?
那您第二个问题是什么
the second question
第二个问题
We reformed the old Chinese learning.
我们革新派对中国旧学
What is the attitude?
究竟是什么态度
Remember what I said today.
今天我说的话你要记住
Because there may be some people in the future
因为将来可能会有一些人
Argue over this issue.
在这个问题上扯皮
My general opinion is that
我总的看法是
Old Chinese studies
中国旧学
Is a part of world scholarship.
是世界学术中的一部分
Confucian Confucianism
儒家孔学
It is a part of the old Chinese school.
是中国旧学中的一部分
Kong Sangang
孔教三纲
Is a part of Confucianism.
是孔学中的一部分
Even a small part.
甚至是很小的一部分
For the existence of value within the responsibility of Confucianism
对于孔学本分之内的价值存在
We have no objection.
我们并不反对
Wait a minute, you're going too far.
等会儿 您说得太绕
I'm a little confused.
我有点糊涂了
So what exactly do you object to?
那您究竟反对的是什么呢
That's a good question.
你这个问题问得好
Right? Then I'll just say it
绕是吧那我直接说
We are opposed to putting some of the
我们反对将一部分中的
Part of the Three Outline of Confucianism
部分的一部分的孔教三纲
Respect for Taoism and tradition
尊为道统
We are also opposed to putting all the
我们也反对将全体的
All the old Chinese studies
全体的全体的中国旧学
They all stepped on each other and said nothing.
都一起踩在脚下 说得分文不值
Why did the reformers attack the three cardinal principles of Confucianism?
革新派为什么要攻击孔教三纲
Except that it is not suitable for the present social life.
除了它不适合现在社会生活之列外
This is also a very important point.
这也是很重要的一点
So you think so.
原来您是这样想的
But Mr. Wu Yu and Mr. Yi Baisha
但是吴虞先生跟易白沙先生
That fierce attitude.
那种激烈的态度
It doesn't give people the impression you said.
给人不是你说那种印象
Didn't I just say that?
刚才我不是说了吗
There are excesses and overcorrections in the debate.
争论当中有过激行为 矫过正
This is inevitable.
这在所难免
This letter of mine
我这封信
I intend
我打算
Published in the next issue of New Youth
在下一期《新青年》 中刊登
If it can't be published, you have to testify for me.
如果登不出来你要给我做证啊
I, Chen Duxiu, am in the New Culture Movement.
我陈独秀在新文化运动中
What is the attitude?
究竟是什么态度
I, Marie.
这个我恕难从命
I think.
我认为啊
It doesn't matter what future generations think of us.
后人怎么看我们并不重要
The important thing is
重要的是
Do we have a clear conscience
我们自己是不是问心无愧
Good point. I agree.
说得好  我同意
You say that like my father said.
你这话像我老子说的
Chen Yannian, remember
陈延年 你记住
About the New Culture Movement
关于新文化运动
Debate between reformers and conservatives
革新派和保守派的争论
I'll only tell you this once today, just this once.
我今天只跟你说一次 只此一次
Look, you're worried when you talk.
您看 您这说着说着又急眼了
All right, let's go, let's go, let's go.
行了 走吧走吧走吧
I've said everything I have to say.
该说的我都说完了
What's the fever?
怎么发烧了
Sister Qun, I'm anxious.
群先姐姐我 我内急
Wait a minute.
等一下啊
We need to go to the bathroom.
我们要上厕所
Solve it by yourself.
憨着 自己解决
classmates
同学们
Girls, come here.
女同学们过来
In a circle
围成一个圈
Boys, stand up and turn around.
男同学们起立 向后转
Boys, come here.
男同学们过来
Come to Su Wu to keep Hu Jie.
来 苏武留胡节不辱
Snow and ice.
雪地又冰天
Worry for nineteen years
穷愁十九年
Be thirsty for snow and hungry for felt.
渴饮雪 饥吞毡
Muyangbian
牧羊北海边
Save the heart and the country.
心存汉社稷
Still not paid back
落犹未还
Be in great difficulty
历尽难中难
Heart as hard as stone.
心如铁石坚
Listen to the sound of building when sitting on the night jam.
夜坐塞上时听筑声
Heartache in the ear
入耳心痛酸
Fellow workers
各位工友们
Now the reactionary government
现在反动政府
I've started to attack the students.
已经开始对学生下手了
Now they have arrested many students.
现在他们抓了很多的学生
Locked up in Peking University.
关在了北京大学里面
The whole country has moved.
全国者都已经动起来了
Our workmates in Shanghai have taken to the streets.
上海的工友已经上街了
Our shop in Changxin can't fall behind.
我们长辛店的可不能落后啊
Can't fall behind, can't fall behind
不能落后 不能落后
Can't lag behind
不能落后
The vast number of workers and friends
广大的工人朋友们
The workers in Shanghai don't just take to the streets.
上海的工人可不仅仅是上街啊
People have issued a strike declaration.
人家发布了罢工宣言
Errenjia
而具人家
We are also going to set up a workers' organization.
还准备要成立一个工人组织
To lead this social movement
要领导这次社会运动
Workers, think about it.
工人朋友们 大家想一想
The working class stands on China's political stage.
工人阶级站在中国的政治舞台上
This is an epoch-making event.
这可是开天辟地的大事情啊
So I appeal to everyone.
所以我呼吁大家
We should also act quickly.
也要赶快行动起来
We should also stand at the forefront of this movement.
我们也要站到这次运动的最前列
okay
好吗
good
好
寿昌先生
守常先生
Zhong lai
仲邂来
Friends!
工人朋友们
Quiet, everybody, quiet.
安静一下 大家安静一下
Let's listen to Zhong Jie.
让我们来听听仲解同学
The situation brought about by the meeting of the students' association
从学联碰头会上带来的情况
Go ahead, please.
你说吧
Fellow workers, fellow masters
各位工友们 各位师傅们
Today is the craziest day for reactionaries.
今天是反动派最为疯狂的一天
Until before.
直到自前为止
We already have about
我们已经有大概
More than a thousand students were arrested.
一千多名同学遭到了逮捕
These classmates are now being held in
这一干多名同学现在被关押在
Law and science of Peking University
北大的法科和理科
There is no water, no food.
那儿没有水 没有食物
No guarantee at all.
完全没有保障
So the Federation of Students decided
所以学联决定
start from tomorrow
从明天开始
Put the goal of struggle
把斗争的目标
Turn into an all-out rescue for the arrested classmates.
转变成为全力营救被捕的同学
We need to electrify the whole country.
我们要通电全国
Use all available means.
动用一切能动用的方式
Force the reactionary government to let them release people.
去逼反动政府 让他们放人
Now the Federation of Students is preparing the declaration.
现在学联正在筹备宣言
And prepare for tomorrow morning.
并准备明天上午一早
Organize five thousand students.
组织五千名同学
March on the streets together in three ways.
分三路一同上街游行
These five thousand students will be in dressing the tomorrow.
这五千名同学明天会统一着装
Carry your own bags and dry food.
背书包 自带行李和干粮
They asked that they must communicate with their arrested classmates.
他们要求必须与被捕的同学
Go to jail together.
一块坐牢
The rest of the students
其余的同学
School-based
以校为单位
Self-organized to the Ministry of Education
自行组织到教育部
The Presidential Palace Police Department went to sit-in demonstration.
总统府 警察厅去静坐 示威
Ask them to release the arrested classmates.
要求他们释放被捕的同学
I have four copies of our rules.
我手里有四份我们的规定
I'll send it to you later.
一会儿会发给大家
Fellow workers and masters
各位工友 各位师傅们
these two days
这两天
We have hundreds of classmates in Peking University.
我们北大已经有好几百名同学
Be violently arrested
被暴力地逮捕
Students from No.1 Middle School and No.4 Middle School tomorrow
明天一中和四中的同学个
Will also help us.
也会来帮助我们
Now we urgently need your help and help.
现在我们急需你们的帮助和援手
Guys, I suggest
工友们 我提议
The meeting broke up after a while.
一会儿散会了
Take each branch factory as a unit.
以各分厂为单位
Everyone is going to take to the streets to support students.
组织大家准备上街声援学生
And go to the presidential palace to petition.
并且到总统府去请愿